H1: Shop and Establishment License
P: The Shops and Establishment act makes sure that both organized and unorganized sectors are providing appropriate working conditions to the labourers. An applicant (Establishment) has to file an online application concerning his state's official portal.
P: WhatΓÇÖs Included?
LI: Choose Expert Assistance Plan
LI: 99% Setup Success Rate
LI: 10+ Years Industry Experience
LI: Application Preparation & Filing
LI: Full Documentation Support
LI: Complete Compliance Support
P: Trusted Experts in Fast, Cost-Effective & Fully Compliant Shop and Establishment License
P: 42825
P: Happy Clients
P: 3500
P: Expert Advisors
P: 50
P: Branch Offices
P: Get Free Expert Consultation
P: Get Update on Whatsapp
LI: Overview
LI: Advantages
LI: Eligibility
LI: Documents
LI: Process
LI: Penalties
LI: Regulation
LI: Why Us
LI: FAQs
H2: Shop and Establishment License - An Overview
P: Most of the businesses in India, including shops, restaurants, cafes, etc., are regulated under the provisions of the Shop and Establishment Act. To regulate the work environment and to ensure the rights of the workers are being protected, it is mandatory to get your business registered under the Shop and Establishments Act. However, the rules and regulations vary from state to state in; which the Act aims at providing proper working conditions to the labourers and taking care of their holidays, wages, and rights.
P: As per the Act, the establishment includes shops, commercial establishments, residential hotels, restraint, eating houses, theatres, or other places of public entertainment and also those establishments as notified by the State government in the official gazette.
P: A shop means any place or premises where goods are sold and services rendered to customers. It includes store-rooms, go-downs, warehouses or workplaces other than a factory, commercial establishment or other places used for public amusement and entertainment. The License is issued to the following establishments: -
LI: Business
LI: Trade
LI: Professions registered under the Shop and Establishment Act.
H2: Benefits of Obtaining Shop and Establishment License
H3: Legal Recognition
P: The Shops and Establishment license provides legal recognition to the respective establishment/shop.
H3: Acts As a Business Proof
P: For further business registrations in India, the Shops and Establishment license acts as a business proof.
H3: Helpful In Opening the Bank Accounts and Other Formalities
P: The registration of Shops and Establishments becomes necessary for reasons like opening a bank account in the name of an establishment/shop.
H3: Provides A Platform for Raising New Investment
P: The Shops and Establishment license helps the proposed entrepreneur in raising investments through loans or venture capital for the proposed business establishment.
H3: Avails The Government Benefits
P: By getting the shop and establishment license, the entrepreneur can avail of the government benefits in a different stage of business.
H3: Saves Time
P: As the process of shop act registration has turned online, it saves time in the registration procedure as well as creates less hectic while in operation.
H2: Eligibility to Obtain a Shop and Establishment License in India
LI: Wholesalers or the retailer's shops and establishments
LI: Service Centres
LI: Warehouses, Storerooms, and go-downs
LI: Additionally, any other working places
LI: Hotels
LI: Eateries and restaurants
LI: Entertainment houses, Amusement parks, Theatres, etc.Bottom of Form
H3: Easy Consultation Support for Shop and Establishment License
P: Complete licensing & compliance support
LI: Expert regulatory guidance
LI: Free 30-Min Advisory
H2: Documents required for obtaining the Shop and Establishment License
P: Below-mentioned Documents are required for Shop and Establishment License-
LI: Id proof such as Aadhar card/PAN card/ voter identification card/ driving license of the employer.
LI: Passport size photograph of the employer
LI: The Affidavit, Cancelled cheque, and Bank statement,
LI: A photo of the establishment/ shop along with the employer
LI: In the case of rented property, a copy of the rent agreement
LI: Any utility bill of the working premises.
H3: Other Documents Required as Per the Establishment or Business Entity
LI: In the case of a trust, a list of the number of trustees
LI: Certificate of incorporation, MOA, and AOA as per the Companies Act
LI: In the case of co-operative societies, a list of the number of members and chairman
LI: Partnership deed with all the important information such as the name of the partners along with their signature and share percentage of partners.
H2: Registration Procedure of Shop and Establishment License
P: Physical Registration Procedure: - Any commercial establishment/shop has to apply for the License to the chief inspector of the respective area within 30 days of commencement of business activities. It is applied through a prescribed form that requires some important information, such as-
LI: The name of the respective employee
LI: Name and address of the establishment
LI: Number of employees in the establishment
LI: The category of the proposed establishment and some other details vary from one state to another.
P: Once applied is reviewed by the inspector, then in the next step license is provided to the establishment. The Shop and Establishment License must be displayed at the premises and should be renewed at the prescribed time. Additionally, it is mandatory to obtain the Shop and Establishment License for all business entities, even if they are working from home.
P: Note- As per the Act, any establishment or Shop in case of closing down the business has to notify the chief inspector in writing before 15 days of closing. The chief inspector further cancels the registration certificate of the establishment or Shop by removing it from the register.
P: Online Procedure for Obtaining a Shop and Establishment License
H3: Visit The Website
P: First of all, an applicant needs to visit the Labour Department website of the respective state (as applicable) and create the user ID and password through the same link.
H3: Fill In the Requisite Details to Create the Profile
P: Below mentioned details are required-
LI: Name of the proposed establishment/shop
LI: Name and details of the employer
LI: Name and details of the employees at that time
LI: Registered establishment address along with NOC or rent agreement (only for rented premises)
LI: PAN card details of the employer
H3: Form A
P: Click on Shop and Establishment Registration Form A.
H3: Fill In the Requisite Details
P: Select the state and district of your shop or establishment and fill in the requisite details asked in the form.
H3: Upload Documents
P: Once the form is filled, click on the Upload Documents, and attach the requisite necessary papers.
H3: Fees
P: After uploading all the Documents, click on the fees button and make the payment.
H3: Checking The Status
P: An applicant can check the status on the under-scrutiny option.
H3: Issuance Of the License
P: If all the Documents are as per the requirements of the act, the certificate shall be issued to the proposed establishment/shop.
P: Note: However, in the case of Physical form Submission, it might take around 15-20 working days for the physical verification and issuance of registration certificate in the major city areas. However, it may vary from one state to another.
H2: Penalties for Shop and Establishment Act
P: It is compulsory for the entire establishment under the Act to obtain Shop and Establishment registration and comply with all the rules and regulations prescribed under the Act.
P: However, in case of any failure in getting registration and following the rules and regulations of the Act, the establishment would be liable to pay the penalty. The amount of penalty would vary from state to state.
H2: Aspects Regulated as per the Provisions of the Shop and Establishments Act
P: The Shop and Establishment Act has made various provisions to regulate the aspects relating to the working of shops and establishments in India. Following are Some Key Aspects Regulated by them: -
LI: Maximum working hours of the employees/ labours
LI: Time duration allotted for meals and rest
LI: Regulating laws to prohibit child labour in factories and other establishments
LI: Women employment
LI: Number of compulsory weekly holidays provided to the employees
LI: Close/off days of the establishments/shops
LI: Opening and closing hours of the establishments/shops
LI: Wages to employees for the holidays
LI: Accident's coverage policies
LI: Preventive measures against fire
LI: Proper ventilation and lighting for workers
LI: Clean and hygienic premises for the workers
LI: Conditions and timing for the payment
LI: Regulation of deductions on the payments
LI: Leave Policy
LI: Dismissal
LI: Employee's proper record keeping
P: Note: More information related to the Shop and Establishment Act can be gathered on the relative state government portal.
H2: CorpBiz Procedure for Shop and Establishment License
LI: Purchase a Plan for Expert Assistance
LI: Add queries regarding Shop and Establishment License
LI: Provide Documents to CorpBiz Expert
LI: Prepare application for Shop and Establishment license + complete all admissibility criteria for preliminary screening
LI: Complete Procedural actions for Shop and Establishment License
LI: Shop and Establishment License at your Doorstep.
H3: Easy Consultation Support for Shop and Establishment License
P: Complete licensing & compliance support
LI: Expert regulatory guidance
LI: Free 30-Min Advisory
H2: Top Questions Regarding on Shop and Establishment License
H3: Is it necessary to take approval from the labor department?
H3: What are the List of Records to be maintained under Shop and Establishment Act?
LI: A register containing all details of employment
LI: Any deduction from salary
LI: Advances issued
LI: Any fine applied
LI: Salary details
LI: Holidays awarded
H3: When does the employee's related information to be submitted according to the act?
H3: When is a Shop and Establishment Act Registration required?
H3: What are the Objectives behind the Shop and Establishment License in India?
LI: To protect the rights and satisfaction of the laborers working in the organized sector such as establishments, hotels, and restaurants as well as in the unorganized sectors.
